Alright. בוקר טוב. Boker tov.
Today's דף daf is כ"ז Chaf Zayin and we begin the new
פרק. perek. You read the משנה mishna yesterday but just for completeness
or whatever, let's read it again today. So the משנה mishna at
the bottom of כ"ו עמוד ב'. Chaf Vav amud bet.
בכל מערבין ומשתתפין, B'chol m'arvin u'mishtatfin, you can do an עירוב eruv
and a שיתוף. shituf. Now the שיתוף shituf is the different חצרות,
chatzerot, the different courtyards as it were or streets to which the
houses open to, all sort of joined together for the מבוי, mavoi,
the alleyway. Now so that says and you learned that at the
end of yesterday as well, the idea that everybody has to join
together with certain with food so it's all considered to be one
ownership. Now there's a parallel issue which is maybe the more basic
building block of עירוב חצרות, eruv chatzerot, when the houses that open
up into these yards or streets all join together so you can
carry from the houses into the yard and from the yard into
the houses. And they also join together in quantity of food. So
logically you would think since it combines מערבין m'arvin which is משתתפין,
mishtatfin, it includes here עירוב חצרות. eruv chatzerot. And if you look
at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says בכל מערבין עירובי חצרות ותחומין. b'chol
m'arvin eruvei chatzerot v'tchumin. However, תוספות Tosafos points out that although that's
one read the גמרא Gemara suggests, that later the גמרא Gemara makes
it clear that עירובי חצרות eruvei chatzerot is only בפת, b'pat, is
only with bread.
So therefore תוספות Tosafos says the real read is בכל מערבין b'chol
m'arvin means עירובי תחומין eruvei tchumin
and עירובי חצרות eruvei chatzerot and שיתופי מבואות shitufei mevo'ot so interestingly
according to the הלכה, halacha, עירובי חצרות eruvei chatzerot which is really
the counterpart to שיתופי מבואות, shitufei mevo'ot, so עירובי חצרות eruvei chatzerot
is bread and the things that you can do any food for
is שיתופי מבואות shitufei mevo'ot and עירובי תחומין. eruvei tchumin. Okay so
that's just to be aware that מערבין m'arvin can mean two things,
according to רש"י Rashi it means both, according to תוספות Tosafos only
עירובי תחומין. eruvei tchumin. So you do that with anything חוץ מן
המים ומן המלח chutz min hamayim u'min hamelach except for water and
salt which are not considered real food. We'll see what the definitions
are later. והכל ניקח בכסף מעשר חוץ מן המים ומן המלח. V'hakol
nikach b'kesef ma'aser chutz min hamayim u'min hamelach. You can use מעשר
ma'aser money, it says that if you don't want to bring up
all of your מעשר שני ma'aser sheni
on the years one, two, four, and five, you have to bring
the second מעשר ma'aser to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. If you don't want to
bring all the food, you transfer the value to money and you
use the money בכל אשר תאוה נפשך b'chol asher t'aveh nafshecha says
the תורה, Torah, whatever your heart desires. But it's not really whatever,
it still has to be food and it can be anything חוץ
מן המים ומן המלח, chutz min hamayim u'min hamelach, excluding water and
salt. הנודר מן המזון, Hanador min hamazon, if you take a vow
and you forbid upon yourself or you forbid the food that anything
that is food, מותר במים ומלח mutar b'mayim u'melach you're still allowed
water and salt. So the theme here being that water and salt
are not considered to be food, not that they're not water necessities
of life, it's ironic actually, two of the most basic necessities of
life are water and salt, but they're not considered to be food.
Okay now we get to the act of making an עירוב eruv
and here we start seeing with תוספות's Tosafos point that the emphasis
becomes by עירוב eruv is not עירובי חצרות eruvei chatzerot but עירובי
תחומין. eruvei tchumin. What is עירובי תחומין? eruvei tchumin? עירובי תחומין eruvei
tchumin is that you're only allowed to travel 2,000 אמות, amot, about
3/5ths of a mile outside of city limits, about a kilometer really.
Okay, so 2,000 אמות amot outside of city limits. There's a debate
whether this is biblical or rabbinic. אל יצא איש ממקומו ביום השבת
Al yetzei ish mimkomo b'yom hashabat according to some ביום השביעי, b'yom
hashvii, thank you, according to some it's biblical but even if it's
biblical the רמב"ם Rambam says it's only like a much larger amount,
I think the רמב"ם Rambam says it is 12 פרסה, parsa, 12
מיל mil or 12 פרסה parsa I'm trying to remember. Anyway it's
much more. You know it's yes, right exactly. So but nevertheless certainly
rabbinically you can't go more than 2,000 אמות, amot, and
that's outside of city limits. Now if you wanted to extend that,
the way you would do it is you would put food, and
here we see the food can be anything except water and salt,
food that's enough for two meals' worth at a certain place outside
of city limits and it would be considered that that's where you
started your שבת. Shabbat.
So therefore if normally
here's your city and it's
2,000 אמות amot in each direction, you sort of square it off
is like this. Okay, then that's where you would start. Now let's
say here you had so let's say though you wanted to go
someplace over here. So what you would do is you would put
your עירוב eruv here and that would give you you know 2,000
אמות amot in each direction and it would let you as long
as this gets you into the you know whatever this would have
to get so that where you're starting שבת Shabbat really where you
start you know it covers those 2,000 אמות. amot. You don't want
to start שבת Shabbat outside of your עירוב. eruv. So because your
food is here it's like you virtually began שבת Shabbat there. So
and that allows you then once שבת Shabbat begins to travel 2,000
אמות amot from that point.
Anyway, we'll talk about the placing of the עירוב Eruv later and
exactly how it extends and is it does it have to actually
reach you or just reach your city and how all those things
work. Okay, but the idea is that it extends, it pulls away,
it doesn't just extend, it shifts where you are where you virtually
begin שבת, Shabbat, so you can travel more in one direction but
less in the other direction.
So it's rabbinic? Isn't this...
This is rabbinic. As I said... So it's rabbinic? Right, this is
rabbinic. And there is an opinion that there is a biblical idea
of תחומים, Techumim, but this is much, much less than the biblical
תחומים, Techumim, the two thousand אמות, Amot, and the idea of making
an עירוב Eruv is a rabbinic institution. Yes?
I have a question. If if you're placing this food, say bread
or whatever it is, outside the city somewhere. Yes. Where there's no
habitation, it's by definition outside the city, isn't it vulnerable to...
Yes, excellent point, excellent point. So one of the things is it
has to be in a protected place. Okay, so we will see
all of that. So there's going to be a lot of discussion.
This is going to be a major discussion. Number one is how
do you do the measuring of the two thousand אמות Amot in
general? Even if you're in the city, if you're outside, where does
it over... what if it overlaps with a city and so on?
And how do you place it and what do you place that
it constitutes a good עירוב? Eruv? These are going to be... this
is going to be a lot easier than the discussion of the
previous two פרקים. Perakim. Okay, so this is the issue about עירוב
תחומין. Eruv Techumin. Now... So can be with... Now מערבין לנזיר ביין
ולישראל בתרומה. Me'arvin le-Nazir be-yayin u-le-Yisrael bi-Trumah. You can do it for
a נזיר Nazir with wine and ישראל Yisrael תרומה Trumah even though
they can't eat it, since it's fit to be eaten by somebody
else. סומכוס אומר בחולין. Sumchus omer be-chullin. סומכוס Sumchus says no, it
has to be unsanctified grain, it has to be fit for you
to eat to count as that's where you're starting שבת, Shabbat, it
has to be a meal that you could eat. ולכהן בבית הפרס,
U-le-kohen be-veit ha-pras, you can put it for a כהן Kohen in
a בית הפרס, Beit ha-Pras, which is a place with a... graves
were plowed over, so rabbinically we're concerned that... we don't let כהנים
kohanim walk there, they might walk over... over bone, but it's a
rabbinic concern and therefore that's okay. רבי יהודה אומר אפילו בין הקברות,
Rabbi Yehuda omer afilu bein ha-kevarot, you can even put it in
the middle of the graveyard, מן שיכול לחוץ לילך ולהאכל min she-yakhol
lachutz lelekh ve-le'akhol
because you can make a מחיצה, mechitzah, you can find a way
to get a כהן Kohen into the graveyard, which the גמרא Gemara
will worry how the... we'll see how you can do that without
transgressing. Now תוספות Tosafot raises the question. You know, when it came
to the nature of the food, the point was was that we
said the first opinion was you didn't have to be able to
eat it as long as somebody could eat it, a ישראל Yisrael
for תרומה Trumah as long as a כהן Kohen could eat it.
How about where it's placed? If the... if let's say... let's say
the food is literally on top of a grave, right? And it's
impossible for a כהן Kohen to get there. Well, why don't we
say: who cares? Somebody else could eat it, right? So תוספות Tosafot
says it seems that there's a difference. It seems that even those
opinions that say that you don't have to be able to eat
it, still say you have to be able to get to it.
Okay? And therefore, while the dominant position, the סתם stam of the
משנה Mishnah is that it can be food you can't eat, it
could be wine and you could be a נזיר, Nazir, it has
to be in a place you can get to, and that's the
issue of a כהן Kohen having the food in the graveyard. Okay?
So we will see more about that in the גמרא. Gemara. Let's
take a look now at the גמרא, Gemara, top of כז עמוד
א. chaf-zayin amud aleph. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, says רבי
יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, אין למדין מן הכללות ואפילו במקום שנאמר בו חוץ.
Ein lemedin min ha-kelalot va-afilu be-makom she-ne'emar bo chutz. You can't learn
from general rules even when it lists the exceptions. So if there's
a place where it says זה הכלל, zeh ha-kelal, this is the
rule, anything that's da-da-da-da-da, this is the law that applies to them,
right? What is the famous... what is it... famous thing, you know,
all people... all people are mortal, you know, Socrates is a person,
Socrates is mortal. Anyway,
what is that called? Syllogism, right. Anyway, so anytime you have anyway,
whatever you have, if you have a rule, all food is חייב
chayav in תרומות ומעשרות, trumot u-ma'asrot, it doesn't really mean all. You
can't trust it. No rule is absolute... no rule can you trust
applies 100 percent of the time, even when the rule lists the
exceptions. So you would think if it's listing the exceptions then it's
telling you nothing else is an exception. No, there might always be
some other exception. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara wants to understand what
did he say this in reference to. מדקאמר, Mi-de-ka-amar, since he's saying
אפילו במקום שנאמר בו חוץ, afilu be-makom she-ne'emar bo chutz, even when
it says the exceptions you can't really trust the rule, מכלל דלאו
הכי קאי, mikhlal de-lav hakhi ka'ei, it sounds like he's talking about
our משנה Mishnah because our משנה Mishnah says בכל מערבין חוץ מן
המים ומן המלח, be-khol me'arvin chutz min ha-mayim u-min ha-melach, with anything
except water and salt. So from רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan's statement, which
is you can't trust that even if it says except, means that
there's going to be a few more things that you can't make
an עירוב eruv with, right? Because he says it's never iron-clad, this
rule. But because he says even when it says חוץ, chutz, it's
not iron-clad, it suggests that he said his original statement in a
context where it didn't say חוץ, chutz, right? So more obvious... so
what is that original context? So the גמרא Gemara says היכא קאי?
heikha ka'ei? דלאו הכי קאי. de-lav hakhi ka'ei. היכא קאי? Heicha kai?
What was רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan referring to when he says you
can't trust a זה הכלל? Zeh Haklal? I
can't trust is not a good word, makes it sound like it's
not being honest, but it's not iron-clad when it says זה הכלל.
Zeh Haklal. So the גמרא Gemara says התם קאי Hasm kai on
the following statement: כל מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא אנשים חייבים ונשים פטורות.
Kol mitzvos asseh shehazman grama anashim chayavim venashim peturos. Any מצות עשה
mitzvot asei that is time-bound, men are obligated and women are exempt.
ושלא הזמן גרמא אחד אנשים ואחד נשים חייבים, Veshelo hazman grama echad
anashim ve’echad nashim chayavim, men and women are both obligated.
So that doesn't say חוץ, chutz, so that's and that would be
an example of a זה הכלל, Zeh Haklal, this is the rule,
which רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says is not iron-clad. So the גמרא
Gemara says וכללא הוא דכל מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא נשים פטורות? Vechlala
hu dechol mitzvat asei shehazman grama nashim peturos? Is that really a
general rule that any positive time-bound מצוות mitzvot women are exempt? הרי
מצה שמחה והקהל. Harei Matzah Simchah veHakhel. How about מצה, Matzah, we
just got through with that, שמחה, Simchah, ושמחת בחגך, Vesamachta bechagecha, and
הקהל? Hakhel? דמצות עשה שהזמן גרמא הוא, Demitzvat asei shehazman grama hu,
those are time-bound מצוות mitzvot ונשים חייבות, venashim chayavos, and women are
חייב. chayav. מצה Matzah we learned that since they're prohibited in אכילת
חמץ, achilat chametz, לא תאכל עליו חמץ שבעת ימים תאכל עליו מצות,
lo tochal alav chametz shivat yamim tochal alav matzot, anybody that's prohibited
in חמץ chametz is obligated in מצה. matzah.
שמחה Simchah it says ושמחת אתה וביתך, Vesamachta ata uveitecha, you and
your household, talking to the men but household meaning the women, so
women are included in the מצוה. mitzvah. And הקהל Hakhel it says
הקהל את העם האנשים והנשים והטף, Hakhel et ha’am anashim vehanashim vehataf,
men, women and children. So these are time-bound מצוות mitzvot that women
are obligated, so that rule does not really is not an iron-clad
principle.
Is this a sidebar or is this questioning if this is really
a כלל? klal?
No, well this is proving רבי יוחנן’s Rabbi Yochanan point that זה
הכלל Zeh Haklal is not iron-clad. So the גמרא Gemara is saying
where did you what would be a case where it didn’t say
חוץ, chutz, which is a more obvious case that you can’t it’s
not iron-clad? So this is the more obvious case that he’s referring
to and then we’ll worry about the cases where even where it
says חוץ. chutz. Now and similarly וכל מצות עשה שלא הזמן גרמא
נשים חייבות, vechol mitzvat asei shelo hazman grama nashim chayavos, any מצות
עשה mitzvot asei that is not time-bound women are obligated. הרי תלמוד
תורה ופריה ורביה ופדיון הבן. Harei Talmud Torah uPeru uRevu uPidyon HaBen.
Here’s three exceptions: teaching תורה Torah or learning תורה, Torah, which the
גמרא Gemara learns from ולמדתם אתם את בניכם בניכם ולא בנותיכם, velimaditem
otam et beneichem beneichem velo benoteichem, your sons and not your daughters,
that women are exempt from תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah. That has very
broad implications to that and a lot of things to say about
that but we're not going to get into that now. And פריה
ורביה, Peru uRevu, also fascinating, although the תורה Torah says to אדם,
Adam, right it says ויאמר להם אלהים פרו ורבו, vayomer lahem Elokim
pru urevu, which is the point that one of the תנאים Tannaim
make. The פסק psak of the גמרא Gemara is that women are
exempt from פריה ורביה Peru uRevu and it learns that out because
the end of the פסוק pasuk says פרו ורבו ומלאו את הארץ
וכבשוה pru urevu umilu et ha’aretz vechivshuha
and conquer the land. So it says oh, who does the conquering?
Obviously it’s the men. So from the end of the פסוק pasuk
you see that the תורה Torah is talking to the men and
not the women. So that’s פריה ורביה. Peru uRevu. And פדיון הבן
Pidyon HaBen is redeeming the first born son that only the father
is obligated and not the mother. The גמרא Gemara learns that from
a connection that only anybody who somebody has to be theoretically in
the category of being נפדה nifdeh of being redeemed to be obligated
to do פדיון. pidyon. Obviously the גמרא Gemara doesn't say that absolutely
because then you would also exclude well no and וכל מצוה vechol
mitzvah well but he's excluded anyway because his son isn't him. I'm
trying to think if there would be an exception. Well I guess
the exception would be a כהן Kohen with his son who's a
בכור.
bechor. I'm not firstborn, I'm not I don't have to be פודה
podeh but anyway non-firstborn is certainly exempt.
Right, so anyway the גמרא Gemara only makes the exception that thing
in terms of of the sex. So anyway, here you see that
this rule isn't is not iron-clad. There's a lot of exceptions in
both directions. So the גמרא Gemara should have phrased this as a
question: how do you say that’s a rule? אלא אמר רבי יוחנן
Ela amar Rabbi Yochanan says רבי יוחנן: Rabbi Yochanan: אין למידין מן
הכללות ואפילו במקום שנאמר בו חוץ. ein lemedin min haklalot ve’afilu bimakom
shene’emar bo chutz. You can’t learn from a כלל, klal, even you
know it’s not iron-clad even when it says חוץ. chutz. So even
when it says חוץ chutz we’ll get to, that’s our משנה, mishnah,
but even but it’s more obvious you can’t learn from it if
it doesn’t even list the exceptions and a good application would be
this rule by מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא. mitzvot asei shehazman grama. I
should say something about this which is I thought what was being
asked, which is a point that Rabbi Saul Berman makes in a
famous article he wrote about this whole issue about women and מצוות
mitzvot a good twenty thirty years ago. Anyway, the question is when
there turns out to be that there are so many exceptions, like
I mean there’s a lot of exceptions here, three on each side,
and how many are actually in this category of מצות עשה שהזמן
גרמא, mitzvot asei shehazman grama, you know that women are exempt from?
So he did a count and he came up with the fact
that there are about as many exceptions as there are things that
actually are fall into the rule, which is pretty funny. So once
that becomes true, the question is how much can you what you
know how
is the כלל klal really telling you something about the nature of
the of what's in and what's out, especially when there are so
many
exceptions? We normally tend to say, oh well why are
women
פטורה petura from מצות עשה? mitzvot asei? explanation. Okay, but if there's
just as many exceptions as there are things that fit to the
rule, how much can that really be explanatory or not, or is
that really what it's really about? So anyway, that is definitely worth
asking, but the point here is that even is that you cannot,
certainly, rules, there are always going to be exceptions to the rule.
רש״י Rashi says it explicitly, right, on אין למדין, Ayn Lemadin, it's
not much really of a question. In other words, if it's
an exception, I mean, you're assuming that the rule is only needed
for things that I wouldn't have known otherwise. Yeah, and the גמרא's
Gemara assuming that.
Why do we need a rule if things have to be enumerated?
You can't rely on it.
Well, because it's a default. In other words, it means like, you
know, if you don't know otherwise, you can assume it falls... he's
not saying... Well, you're right, it's a good point. When he says
אין למדין, Ayn Lemadin, does אין למדין Ayn Lemadin mean that you
can't even, like, by default apply the הלכה, halacha, you know,
that you have to prove everything? I think it's somewhere in between.
I think it's more like, you know, you can't sort of blindly
apply the rule. You have to like, you know, oh well we
have this following rule, like you have to do a little bit
of research to make sure that this like thing isn't one of
the exceptions, isn't an exception. Like a memory device? No, I
mean, I do think it's like a default assumption, but I just
think that if... you mean like why did the תנא Tanna bother
to say it?
Because
I think that there's a gap between saying we don't know at
all what the הלכה halacha is by any particular food, whether you
can use it for an עירוב eiruv and every food you have
to figure out what the הלכה halacha is, as opposed to saying,
no, your default assumption is you could use it but there might
be a few non-enumerated exceptions and you have to clarify, you know,
whether your thing might be in that category or not. So you
do a little research and you... yeah, I can't quite... I didn't
see anyone indicate that this was a problem, so I'm going to
assume it's okay.
You know, you follow the rule, the rule applies but not
in the face of contrary evidence. Right, and not... and maybe not
also... רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan goes further. He says אין למדין מן
הכללות, Ayn Lemadin min haklalos, meaning which I think does also mean
a little bit like you can't automatically assume a הלכה halacha based
on a rule, you might need to do a little research, you
know. But certainly, right, but certainly it doesn't mean like it doesn't
serve a purpose, right. But it's a good point because אין למדין
מן הכללות Ayn Lemadin min haklalos sounds more than just like, you
know, don't reject contrary evidence. It sounds even more like
you can't necessarily assume the rule applies. All right, let's take a
look at the other case. אמר אביי Amar Abaye ואי תימא רבי
ירמיה ve'isayma Rabbi Yirmiya אף אנן נמי תנינא, af anan nami tanina,
עוד כלל אחד אמרו od klal echad amru אחר אמרו, acher amru,
they said another general rule. So notice כלל, klal, it says, so
it's not זה הכלל, zeh haklal, but anyway this is a משנה
Mishnah in זבים. Zavim. כל שנישא על גבי הזב טמא. Kol she'nisa
al gabei hazav tamei. Anything that a זב zav is carrying is
טמא. tamei. Now
the general rule is that if you have something that is טמא,
tamei, you are טמא tamei by touching it, and some things you're
טמא tamei even without touching it, but even by like moving it
even indirectly or even by carrying. Okay, this is called טומאת היסט,
tumas hesset, and you know, and you know, if by משא massa
if you carry it... so for example נבילה, neveilah, if you carry
a נבילה neveilah or a מת, meis, right, you
know, of a dead body, so even by moving it or carrying.
Now a זב zav is interesting because a זב zav is the...
so if I were to carry a זב, zav, even without touching
him, I would be טמא. tamei. But if a זב zav carries
something, that's normally not what you have. You normally don't have the
טמא tamei object carrying something else, except here the טמא tamei object
happens to be a person so he can actually do the act
of carrying. So the טומאה tumah is not טומאת משא tumas massa
per se, it's learned out from a פסוק pasuk that actually is
called עליונו של זב, elyono shel zav, what a זב zav is
wearing. If you look at רש״י, Rashi, he says כל שנישא על
גבי הזב, kol she'nisa al gabei hazav, עליונו של זב. elyono shel
zav. רש״י Rashi about ten lines before the lines get wide. דכתיב
וכל אשר יהיה תחתיו. Dechsiv vechol asher yihyeh sachtav.
Anything that's under the זב zav is טמא tamei that he sits
on. ואמרו בפרק בנות כותים, Ve'amru beperek Benos Kusim, מאי תחתיו, mai
sachtav, אי נמי מתחת לזב אנו מחויבים, ee nami mitachas lezav anu
mechuyavim, אלא בכל שיהיה הזב תחתיו. ela bechol she'yihyeh hazav sachtav.
Anything that the זב zav is underneath. So it's a funny read
of the פסוק. pasuk. The פסוק pasuk really says anything underneath the
זב zav becomes טמא, tamei, but we read it anything the זב
zav is underneath, it's טמא tamei because the זב zav is carrying.
So we have this interesting idea by a זב, zav, which is
called that even though the טמא tamei object as it were, the
זב, zav, is carrying something, wearing something, it becomes טמא. tamei. Now
תוספות Tosafos has a question whether that's really just a form of
טומאת היסט tumas hesset or not, of טומאה tumah of moving or
something else, but anyway that's one הלכה halacha and that you should
just be aware is a not your classic case of משא. massa.
So כל שנישא על גבי הזב, kol she'nisa al gabei hazav, anything
the זב zav is carrying,
טמא. tamei. וכל שהזב נישא עליו, Vekol hazav nisa alav, now anything
that a זב zav is being carried on,
טהור tahor is טהור. tahor. Now this doesn't mean that well
we'll... the אדם. adam. If I the אדם adam am carrying a
זב, zav, that's what I said is classic טומאת משא. tumas massa.
I am carrying the טמא tameh object. Okay, and then I am
טמא. tameh. Let's say a זב zav is being carried held up
by an object. So if the object that he is being held
supported by is a seat or a chair or a bed, that's
the הלכה halacha of a משכב mishkav or a מושב. moshav. That
anything a זב zav sits on or lies on, if it's made
for sitting or lying, it's defined as the משכב mishkav or the
מושב moshav of the זב zav and it becomes an אב הטומאה.
av hatumah. Even if he doesn't actually touch it, you know, if
there's like 10 cushions like the princess and the pea, because it's
about... it's about... it's about its being his משכב mishkav or his
מושב, moshav, his seat. But if he's on top of things that
are not made for sitting or lying, let's say he's on top
of like 10 stacked tables or whatever, one table and he's, you
know, and he's sitting on it and he's not touching it, you
know, his clothes are on it, so then the table does not
become טמא. tameh. Okay, so that is the rule. Anytime that a
זב zav is... anything a זב zav carries is טמא, tameh, anything
that... that carries a זב zav is טהור, tahor, unless it is
a person carrying the זב zav or a משכב mishkav and a
מושב. moshav. Now, so that's the
חוץ. chutz. So ותו ליכא? v'tu leka? So now the גמרא Gemara
says, is that really the only exceptions? ואיכא מרכב. v'ika merkav. What
about a מרכב? merkav? Not only a משכב mishkav or a מושב
moshav that is underneath him becomes טמא, tameh, it's even a מרכב
merkav like a saddle, something that you ride on. So the גמרא
Gemara says one minute, האי מרכב היכי דמי? hai merkav heichi dami?
What do you mean by a מרכב? merkav? אי יתיב עלה, i
yasiv ala, if it's... if it's a saddle that he sits on,
היינו מושב, hainu moshav, it's in the מושב moshav category. So why
do you bother set... now the תורה Torah speaks about a מרכב,
merkav, כל המרכב אשר ירכב עליו
הזב. kol hamerkav asher yirkav alav hazav. And actually there's a slightly
different הלכה halacha between a saddle and a normal seat. So the
גמרא Gemara does not mean to say here that a מרכב merkav
is identical to a מושב. moshav. What it means, look, when we
said except for things he sits on, we included saddles, you know,
as... you know, that doesn't prove that's not in our list, obviously
it includes other types of things including saddles, even if saddles has
slightly different הלכה. halacha. So the גמרא Gemara says, אנן הכי קאמרינן.
anan hachi kaamrinan. No, this is what we're saying. ואיכא גבא דאוכפא.
v'ika gavva d'ukfa.
What about the, I don't know what it's called, the horn of
the saddle? What's the thing you... pommel? Pommel. I think p-o-m-m-e-l.
Okay. What about the pommel? That, he's not really... it's not where
his תחת tuchas is as it were, but it sort of supports
his sitting and that is considered also a מרכב merkav to be
טמא, tameh, even if he doesn't touch it. דתניא, d'tanya, we learned...
But isn't it all part of the saddle though? What? But isn't
it all part of the saddle he's sitting on?
Yeah, so
you mean why isn't it just טמא tameh because the whole object
is one unit?
Well, I guess you could imagine a case where he was sitting
just on top of the, the... that part, that pommel, not sitting
on the... on the saddle. So if that itself were not considered
a מרכב, merkav, you know, were not considered a part of sitting.
It's actually an interesting question, right? Let's say you have a couch,
I... I never thought about this, let's say you have a couch
and you know, you... you know, although some people sit on the
arms of a couch, you know, you... you know, your parents, yeah,
whatever, you're not supposed to, it's not made for sitting on the
arms, and... and the זב zav was sitting on the arm of
the couch. Would that become a משכב mishkav or מושב, moshav, right?
It's part of an object that you sit on but this isn't
part of the object you're supposed to be sitting on. I don't
know. I don't know. I have to check into that. But that's
what I was imagining would be the issue here about this pommel
of the saddle, that even though it's connected, it's not a part
that you necessarily sit on. So the גמרא Gemara says,
האוכף טמא מושב. ha'ukaf tameh moshav. So the actual saddle is טמא
מושב. tameh moshav. והתפוס טמא מרכב v'hatapus tameh merkav is מרכב merkav
which is a similar טומאה tumah but it's a little bit less
in... there's one area where it's... where it's slightly less than that
of a מושב. moshav. So... so anyway when it excluded משכב mishkav
and מושב, moshav, by the way that also sounds like even when
you sit on the saddle, touching the pommel has a different הלכה.
halacha. So I'll have to check into this and get back to
you. It is interesting that even... how could you define that status
of מושב moshav not apply to the whole thing that you just
sat on... to the... you know, but anyway, so you see that
there is this other category called מרכב merkav which wasn't listed. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אלא שמע מינה אין למדין מן הכללות ואפילו
במקום שנאמר בו חוץ. ela shma mina ein lemedin min haklalos v'afilu
b'makom shenemar bo chutz. You can't learn from when it says זה
כלל zeh klal even when it gives the exceptions. Now, that is
not the world's greatest example because again, מרכב merkav is not substantially
different than מושב, moshav, so I'd like, you know, another example would
be more helpful. So now he gets to אמר רבינא ואיתימא רב
נחמן אף אנן נמי תנינא. amar Ravina v'isaima Rav Nachman af anan
nami tanina. Now we also taught in our משנה, mishnah, and now
this is why it's being brought here, בכל מערבין ומשתתפין חוץ מן
המים ומן המלח, Bechol me'arvin u-mishtatfin chutz min hamayim u-min hamelach, that
you can do עירוב eiruv and שיתוף shituf with anything except from
the water and from the salt. So the גמרא Gemara says תו
ליכא, tu leka, are there no other exceptions? ואיכא כמיהין ופטריות, Ve'ika
kmeihim u-pitriot,
what about like vegetables and fun not vegetables mushrooms and fungi? So
those are not normally considered to be things that grow from the
ground, they're fungi,
so those should be excepted. I'll talk about that in a minute,
let's just finish. אלא שמע מינה, Ella shma mina, even though there
are more exceptions, what do you see? אין למדים מן הכללות, Ein
lomedim min haklalos, you cannot learn from the כללות, klalos, ואפילו במקום
שנאמר בו חוץ, v'afilu b'makom shene'emar bo chutz, even where it says
חוץ, chutz, there can sometimes be more exceptions. So just to first
get back to those points and then talk about the mushrooms, you
know,
the question is what does אין למדים ein lomedim mean? My initial
assumption was that אין למדים ein lomedim just meant like, you know,
don't reject contrary evidence. Oh well obviously we don't rule that way
because we know it goes against our principle. No, sometimes you'll find
exceptions to the rule and that's possible and you shouldn't reject it.
But אין למדים ein lomedim does seem to go further and אין
למדים ein lomedim does seem to say like don't פסקן pasken based
on general rules. The general rule is like a rule of thumb,
a default assumption, but you know you might require a little clarification,
you
know double check things, make sure something is not an exception to
the rule before you go ahead and you actually פסקן pasken by
it. That sounds a little bit more what Rabbi Yochanan is saying
of אין למדים. ein lomedim. But again the rule does serve a
purpose, it lets you know what the default assumption is and you
know and presumably you don't have to
prove every individual case, you just have to do enough to indicate
that this is not an exception. Now I want to say something
about the mushrooms and the fungi here. Which case is it being
excepted from? So the language of our גמרא Gemara sounds like it's
being excepted from the first line about עירוב eiruv and שיתוף מבואות.
shitufei mavos. Now why are fungi excepted? Meaning you don't need the
הלכה halacha about גידולי קרקע, gidulei karka, doesn't have to be things
that grow from the ground, why would you exclude fungi? So תוספות
Tosafot says you exclude them because they're not fit to be eaten
in their raw state. I don't know, plenty of people I know
eat raw mushrooms. Anyway, תוספות Tosafot says this is one area where
the הלכה halacha of שיתופי עירוב shitufei eiruv and שיתוף shituf have
a higher demand than that of things like מעשר. maaser. מעשר, maaser,
you can buy raw meat with your מעשר maaser money. It doesn't
have to be fit to eat right now. But if you're going
to make it considered like we're all together in one house or
I started my שבת Shabbat in one place because the food is
there, it has to be food that's fit to be eaten to
be considered like that's really my place. Right? Raw food is not
going to do me any good that that's considered significant as if
I started שבת Shabbat there. So תוספות Tosafot says that this is
an important difference. Although in the משנה mishnah it sounds like these
are all roughly the same, תוספות Tosafot says by עירוב חצרות eiruv
chatzeros and שיתופי מבואות shitufei mavos and
עירובי תחומין, eiruvoi techumin, the food has to be in a state
where it's fit to be eaten. So if you wouldn't eat it
in its raw state, no good. But again of course by מעשר
maaser you can buy raw meat with your מעשר maaser money. That's
תוספות's Tosafot read. And that's his פשט pshat of כמיהין ופטריות. kmeihim
u-pitriot. Now look though at the little aleph here of the גר"א,
Gra, חוץ מן המים והמלח, chutz min hamayim ve-hamelach, נכתב בצדו, nichtav
batziddo, do you see that? That little aleph in brackets, I don't
know where it appears in your גמרא. Gemara. Anyway, in the הגהות
הגר"א hagahos haGra it says נכתב בצדו וכולו. nichtav batziddo ve-chulu. Okay,
now you would think that that's like a meaningless addition. The גר"א
Gra adds the words to the גמרא, Gemara, what about the הלכה
halacha of חוץ מן המים והמלח וכולו, chutz min hamayim ve-hamelach ve-chulu,
etc. So the reason the גר"א Gra added etc., any guesses why
he would have added the words
etc.? It's our משנה. mishnah.
Why would he have added the words etc.?
It's quoting, in other words it's indicating that...
Yeah, so he's saying the גמרא Gemara is not referring to the
first part of the משנה. mishnah. It's referring to a later part
of the משנה. mishnah. What it's referring to is the מעשר שני
maaser sheni מעשר maaser part of the משנה. mishnah. That by מעשר
maaser you cannot use your מעשר maaser money for fungi. Why? And
if you look at the next גר"א, Gra, ואיכא כמיהין ופטריות, ve'ika
kmeihim u-pitriot, he says תורת כהנים פרק א׳ פסקא ח׳ Torat Kohanim
perek aleph piska chet and he refers to a תורת כהנים Torat
Kohanim which relates to the issue about your מעשר maaser money, that
it is not fungi are not גידולי קרקע. gidulei karka. They don't
grow from the ground. So if that might be so they could
be excluded from this category of מעשר maaser money. We'll see in
a minute as we continue today what's excluded from the מעשר. maaser.
So the גר"א Gra actually reads this different than תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות
Tosafot reads what are fungi excluded from? They're excluded from עירובי חצרות
eiruvei chatzeros and שיתוף shituf or עירובי תחומין eiruvoi techumin because they're
raw and can't be eaten in their raw state, whatever that means.
And the גר"א Gra excludes it from מעשר maaser because it doesn't
grow from the ground.
And we understand we had fungi from מעשר maaser though.
We had it already. We'll see what the no, מעשר שני, maaser
sheni, not... Yeah, but it grows from
decaying material. It's attached to the ground
but it doesn't grow from the ground. That's what the גמרא Gmara
says in another place. It's not considered גידולי קרקע. Gidulei Karka. Okay?
Right, that's what I thought, so
for מעשר Maaser
we all knew that already from other places though.
Okay, yeah, alright, so let's take a look.
So now the גמרא Gmara continues. So that's anyway another thing that
you can't even trust it when it says חוץ, Chutz, but it's
interesting whether that's a difference by עירובי תחומין Eruvei Techumin or whether
it's by מעשר. Maaser. Now the גמרא Gmara continues: הכל ניקח בכסף
מעשר. Hakol Nikach B'Kesef Maaser.
Now we get to the מעשר Maaser issue. You can buy anything
with מעשר Maaser money except water and salt. רבי אלעזר ורבי יוסי
ברבי חנינא. Rabbi Elazar v'Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Chanina. So it's a debate
between רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar and רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא. Rabbi Yose
b'Rabbi Chanina. חד מתני אעירוב Chad masni a'Eruv וחד מתני אמעשר. v'chad
masni a'Maaser.
One says the following statement regarding עירוב Eruv and the other says
it regarding מעשר, Maaser, the statement we're about to say. חד מתני
אעירוב. Chad masni a'Eruv. One says it by עירוב. Eruv. לא שנו
אלא מים בפני עצמן ומלח בפני עצמן. Lo shanu ela mayim bifnei
atzman v'melach bifnei atzman. When can you not use water or salt
if you use them by themselves? שאין מערבין, She'ein maarvin, that you
can't make an עירוב Eruv with them. אבל במים ומלח מערבין יחד.
Aval bemayim umelach maarvin yachad. Interesting, מערבין, maarvin, מערבין maarvin means different
things in this line. But water and salt mixed together, right, מערבין,
maarvin, that would be good because salt water is like a dip.
So water by itself is a, right, water by itself is a
liquid, it's not a food. Salt is a, you know, it's a
spice or like a nutrient, but you don't eat salt. It's not
a food. But presumably sauces and dips are considered types of food.
But not like sea water. So salt water, right, edible salt water.
So salt water would be a food and you could make an
עירוב Eruv with that. Okay. וחד מתני אמעשר. V'chad masni a'Maaser.
One says this by מעשר. Maaser. לא שנו אלא מים בפני עצמו
ומלח בפני עצמו. Lo shanu ela mayim bifnei atzmo v'melach bifnei atzmo.
You can't use salt by itself and water by itself. שאין ניקחין,
She'ein nikchin, that you can't buy. אבל מים ומלח ניקחין בכסף מעשר,
Aval mayim umelach nikchin b'kesef Maaser, but salt water you can. Now,
מאן דמתני אמעשר, Man de masni a'Maaser, if it's true by מעשר
Maaser you can buy it with salt water, you can use it
to buy salt water, כל שכן אעירוב, Kol shekein a'Eruv, certainly by
עירוב. Eruv. Because עירוב Eruv we're going to see, מעשר Maaser has
more limits what you can use for מעשר. Maaser. So if we
even allow salt, if we'll allow something by מעשר, Maaser, we're certainly
going to allow it by עירוב. Eruv. עירוב Eruv isn't based on
a פסוק, pasuk, it's not as limited of a category. ומאן דמתני
אעירוב, U'man de masni a'Eruv,
but if you allow it by עירוב, Eruv, אבל למעשר לא. aval
l'Maaser lo. You would not allow it by מעשר. Maaser. מעשר Maaser
is a category that might be more narrow. מאי טעמא? Mai Taama?
פרי בעינן. Pirei ba'inan. Because by מעשר Maaser it's not really just
about food, it's really about a fruit, meaning something that is sort
of born by something else, you know, whether it's, whether it's animals
or whether it's fruit or vegetables. But we need this idea of
a fruit and water and salt which are basically minerals, you know,
and liquid and they're not something that's created by something else, that
would not be in the category. And we're going to see in
a minute that idea. So this is the principle that מעשר Maaser
is more likely to be a smaller category. By עירוב Eruv it's
basically about food, whereas by מעשר Maaser it's based on a פסוק
pasuk and based on that פסוק pasuk it might have certain parameters
that it's not enough to be food, might have to be a
fruit, conceptual abstract idea of fruit or other types of limits. Now
I should mention that תוספות Tosfos again, here's where תוספות Tosfos makes
this point: there is one case in which עירוב Eruv does demand
more than מעשר. Maaser. תוספות Tosfos says the עירוב Eruv has to
be fit to be eaten in the state it is, whereas the
מעשר Maaser money you can buy stuff that's raw. And again for
תוספות Tosfos that's the issue about the mushrooms. But the general assumption
putting that aside is that no actually the מעשר Maaser category is
a smaller one, has to be fruit, maybe has to be גידולי
קרקע Gidulei Karka and so on, and whereas the עירוב Eruv category
is just about food. Yes.
Because the point is that it's sort of like, you know, you
have a meal there, מזון שתי סעודות, Mazon Shetei Seudot, right, so
it's to establish residence and all that. Yes. But what's the point
of having a dip if you can't have anything else with it?
Nobody's just gonna eat the dip.
So then shouldn't that be... I understand. You know, but the point
gets to be, I mean, you know, חז"ל Chazal make formal, formal
requirements. So you should be glad that sometimes they leave it at
the abstract sort of quantified, you know, just state. Yeah.
But still, you say something that people, not a lot of people
will do that.
Okay, okay, well that's why, I understand that's why they had to
say it. But okay. Alright, let's take a look, but you are
right, it doesn't necessarily mean that you can,
it doesn't mean that you can what do you call it, it
doesn't mean that, it doesn't mean that you can necessarily eat this
straight as a whole meal. It is a good question because you
need מזון שתי סעודות. Mazon Shetei Seudot. So would you need the
amount of salt that would go together with food of two סעודות?
seudot? I'm not sure. It's a good question. All right, let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gmara. So now we're going to get
into what are the definitions of כסף מעשר. Kesef Maaser. Of, of,
that what can you buy with כסף מעשר. Kesef Maaser. Okay. כי
אתא רב יצחק מתני אמעשר. Ki ata Rav Yitzchak masni a'Maaser. Now
רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak when he came from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
he said this by מעשר Maaser that you can buy. Can do
it with מעשר ma'aser that you can buy salt water with מעשר.
ma'aser. אמרו לו, Amru lo, they said, and they said to him,
מיתיבי, Meisivei, they asked on this, היי בית יהודה בן גדיש לפני
רבי אליעזר, hei Beis Yehuda ben Gadish lifnei Rabbi Eliezer, so רבי
יהודה בן גדיש Rabbi Yehuda ben Gadish testified in front of רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer שבבית אבא היו לוקחין ציר בכסף מעשר. shebe'es Abba
hayu lokchin tzir bekessef ma'aser. My father's house they would buy ציר,
tzir, which is fish brine, with מעשר ma'aser money. אמרו לו, Amru
lo, he said to him, שמא לא שמעת אלא כשעירבו דגים מעורבין
בהן. shema lo shamata ela k'she'irvei dagim me'uravin bahen. Maybe that's only
if it had chunks of fish mixed up into them,
but you could not normally use it for fish brine. So here
there's a debate if you could use it for fish brine. Now
fish brine is a type of a salt water, but as the
גמרא Gemara says, it's more than salt water. ואפילו רבי יהודה בן
גדיש, ve'afilu Rabbi Yehuda ben Gadish, even רבי יהודה בן גדיש, Rabbi
Yehuda ben Gadish, לא קאמר אלא בציר, lo ka'amar ela betzir, he
only said it by fish brine, דשומנא דפירא הוא. deshumnah depeirah hu.
It has the fat of the fruit, meaning the fish is a
type of again fruit here in the abstract sense, it's produced by
another fish. So fish itself is okay. So you could say the
brine that emerges from a fish is a product of the fish.
So you could say that's what he says. At most though he
says fish brine. אבל מים ומלח, aval mayim umelach, straight salt water,
לא לא, lo lo, would not.
So how could anybody claim that straight salt water is okay? So
אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav Yosef, said רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, לא
נצרכה, lo nitzrecha, top of כ"ז ע"ב, chof zayin amud bais,
it's not required to say this, excuse me one second, this stupid
thing, okay, לא נצרכה אלא שנתן לתוכן שמן. lo nitzrecha ela shenasan
lesochan shemen.
We're talking that you put some oil into it. So if you
put some oil into it, so that's a better type of a
dip, salt water with oil, and that's why you can use מעשר
שני ma'aser sheni because of the oil. Now what's the problem with
that answer? You're right, basically you can't use מעשר שני ma'aser sheni
on salt water, but we're talking that you put oil into it.
So what's the problem with that answer?
Why do you have to tell me, what do you mean by
telling me you can use your מעשר שני ma'aser sheni money to
buy salt water if at the end of the day you're telling
me it's only salt water that has oil in it and it's
only allowed because you're because of the oil. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says, אמר ליה אביי ותיפוק ליה משום שמן. amar leh Abaye
vesifokei mishum shemen. So you're basically saying you can use your מעשר
שני ma'aser sheni money for the oil. So what do you mean
by telling me you can use it for the salt water?
לא, lo, says the גמרא, Gemara, no, צריכא, tzricha, you need it
for the case שנתן דמי מים ומלח בהבלאה. shenasan dmei mayim umelach
bahavla'ah.
Because I have $10 of מעשר שני ma'aser sheni money. You're selling
me $10 worth of salt water oil dip. Point is of that
$10, $2 is going to the salt water. Right? So I am
spending $2 of מעשר שני ma'aser sheni money on the salt water
content of this dip.
So what, so you can apply to the, take that to the
extreme, say anything that has water and salt in it, part of
what you're paying...
So that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to say, that you're, this
idea of הבלאה havla'ah works. As long as basically you're primarily paying
for the prime ingredient, the fact that there's some extra money that's
going for the other ingredients, they can be בהבלאה. bahavla'ah. הבלאה havla'ah
sort of means like you know swallowed up. So you're basically saying
I'm buying you know the oil of it and the salt water
part sort of comes for free even though part of the money
really is being paid for the salt water. And that's the חידוש.
chiddush. So the גמרא's Gemara now going to explore this. בהבלאה מי
שרי? bahavla'ah mi sharei? Is that really permissible to use your מעשר
ma'aser money really for partly for something that you can't use מעשר
ma'aser but you sort of include it with the whole purchase?
They kind of have to, you buy meat it's salted. I know.
So that's basically what the גמרא's Gemara going to say, that almost
anything you buy, some of the money you're paying for is for
non-מעשר ma'aser products, right? So that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to
say. But even in the case where it's like you know very
obvious. דתניא, de'tanya,
yes, and we talked, דתניא de'tanya sometimes is a proof. בן בג
בג אומר, Ben Bag Bag omer, בבקר, babakar, you know it says,
the פסוק pasuk says בכל אשר תאוה נפשך. bechol asher te'aveh nafshecha.
You can use the מעשר ma'aser money for anything your heart desires.
בבקר ובצאן וביין ובשכר, babakar uvatzon uvayayin uvashichar,
with cattle and sheep, oil and wine, and wine and mead, and
you know anything you want. Okay. But then he gave you a
list. So what is the list coming to teach me? So בבקר,
babakar, with cattle, מלמד שלוקחין בקר אגב עורו. melamed shelokchin bakar agav
oro.
You can buy the cattle even though some money for that cattle
is for the leather of the cattle, which is not a legitimate
use of money because it's not food. ובצאן, uvatzon, you can buy
sheep with it, מלמד שלוקחין צאן אגב גיזתה. melamed shelokchin tzon agav
gizosah.
You can buy a sheep even if it has wool that you
will shear first and make a profit off of that wool. You
can pay the full value of the sheep out of מעשר ma'aser
money. וביין, uvayayin, wine, מלמד שלוקחין יין אגב קנקנו.
melamed shelokchin yayin agav
kankanno.
When you buy wine, some of the money is going to the
bottle. You don't have to worry about that. Okay. ובשכר, uvashichar, and
with mead, מלמד שלוקחין תמד משהחמיץ. melamed shelokchin temed mishehikmitz.
One way they would sort of make this mead is that they
would take you know
lees of wine and wait for it to like sort of... Wait
for it to like sort of ferment or החמיץ, hichmitz, turn a
little sharp, and then they put water in it and that would
become some type of a beer. So there also a lot of
what is the ingredients there is water. And nevertheless, it's okay. So
here you see if you buy one product, even though some of
the cost goes for the non-legitimate מעשר, maaser, you know, something that
by itself you couldn't use מעשר maaser money, you can buy it
and pay the full price since it's basically one product. And that's
what the חידוש chidush is about the oil and the salt water.
אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, מאן דמתרגם לי
בבקר אליבא דבן בג בג. man demitargem li bivakar aliba d'ben bag
bag. Now
Rabbi Yochanan says okay, that's all very nice, but within this approach
that he learned out from each one of these words an aspect
of this idea of הבלעה, havla, of getting things as a package
deal, I still don't get why you needed the word בבקר. bakar.
You could have learned it from all the other words. So if
I can find somebody that can explain to me the need, the
use of the word בבקר bakar according to Ben Bag Bag, מובילנא
מאניה אבתריה לבי מסותא. movilna manei avatrei l'vei masuta. This is a
funny phrase the Gemara uses, but it says it a couple times,
I will be so grateful I will take his clothes after him
to the bathhouse. I'll be his bathhouse attendant if you could just
explain to me why Ben Bag Bag needs the word בבקר. bakar.
I get all the other words. I don't see what בבקר bakar
is doing in the פסוק pasuk according to Ben Bag Bag. And
now we're going to explain what the problem is. מאי טעמא? Mai
taama? What's the reason that he is sort of saying this? כולהו
צריכי. Kulehu tzrichi. I understand why you need all those words, לבר
מ'בבקר', levar mibivakar, except I don't understand why you need the word
בבקר, bakar, דלא צריך, delo tzarich, it's not needed according to Ben
Bag Bag's דרשה. drasha. מאי צריכי? Mai tzrichi? How are they needed?
אי כתב רחמנא בבקר, ei ktav Rachmana bivakar, had it said cattle,
הוי אמינא בבקר הוא דמזדבן אגב ריפא, hava amina bakar hu demizdaben
agav ripa, fine, you can pay for the cattle with its skin
because משום דגופיה הוא, mishum degufei hu, it's literally part of the
same body. אבל צאן אגב גיזתה, Aval tzon agav gizatah, maybe you
cannot pay with מעשר maaser money the full cost including the cost
of the shearings of the wool. דלאו גופיה הוא, delav gufeih hu,
because the wool is not, even if it's still on the body,
is not considered the same degree as part of the body as
the actual skin. And it grows and it gets shaved off as
opposed to the skin which always remains on. So maybe you wouldn't
be allowed to do הבלעה havla in that case. It's not as
much one unit. אימא לא, Eima lo, maybe you wouldn't be allowed.
ואי כתב רחמנא בצאן, ve'ei ktav Rachmana batzon, had it said that,
אגב גיזתה, agav gizatah, that you can spend do it together
with the shearings, הוי אמינא משום דמחובר, hava amina mishum demichubar, fine
it's all connected like Michael said, that I understand it's one unit
and you could pay full cost. אבל יין אגב קנקנו, Aval yayin
agav kankanno, wine with the bottle, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe those
are clearly separable objects, maybe you can't pay for the cost of
the bottle. ואי כתב רחמנא ביין, ve'ei ktav Rachmana beyayin, had it
just said wine, הוי אמינא משום דהיינו נטירותיה, hava amina mishum dehainu
netiruteih, because the bottle is protecting it. Without the bottle you can't
hold on to the wine. אבל תמד משהחמיץ, Aval tamad mishehichmitz, but
using this type of a beer or whatever that was made from,
you know, from some
fermented grape, דקפיא
דעלמא הוא, dikpaya d'alma hu, that's not even really like, you know,
a real fruit product is in it. It's only like the sharpness.
You know, the amount that's being contributed here by the grapes is
very little. And therefore, you know, just and therefore
maybe it's not even considered like you have enough here to be
really that it's really a מעשר maaser product. Fundamentally this is just
water. אימא לא, Eima lo, I might think that you could not
use spend your מעשר maaser money on something that is fundamentally water.
So כתב רחמנא שכר, ktav Rachmana shechar, you know, it's sort of
like what would be an example? I don't know, like if you
basically had water and you added a little bit of like lemon,
you squirted in a lemon, not made lemonade, but just to give
it water with a little lemony taste. So fundamentally it's all water.
It has a little lemony taste. So you're going to spend your
מעשר maaser money on that? No, you know, it's not really lemon.
Okay. אימא לא. Eima lo. So therefore כתב רחמנא שכר, ktav Rachmana
shechar, it had to say שכר. shechar. So that's why it had
to say all of them. Now, of course you would say why
not tell me the biggest חידוש chidush and don't tell me the
other things? So they'll say no, even I understand why you can't
go in the opposite way. You couldn't have just said שכר. shechar.
ואי כתב רחמנא שכר, ve'ei ktav Rachmana shechar, had it just said
שכר, shechar, הוי אמינא מאי שכר דבילה קעילית, hava amina mai shechar
dveilah ke'ilit, I would have said that שכר shechar does not literally
mean like mead or beer, it means this type of a these
type of special dates called דבילה קעילית, dveilah ke'ilit, which are somewhat
intoxicating. דפירא הוא, depira hu, that's literally fruit. So if it just
said שכר shechar I couldn't have figured it all out. אבל יין
אגב קנקנו, Aval yayin agav kankanno, I would have thought that the
idea of הבלעה havla doesn't apply. Maybe wine together with the bottle,
אימא לא, eima lo, maybe you couldn't. ואי כתב רחמנא יין אגב
קנקנו, ve'ei ktav Rachmana yayin agav kankanno, had it said wine and
I could have inferred okay, you can do wine with the
bottle, דהיינו נטירותיה, dehaynu netiruteih, I would say fine, that idea that
you can pay for the whole cost is only wine with the
bottle because without the bottle it you need the bottle to protect
it. You couldn't, you know, you couldn't do anything with wine. wine
doesn't have a bottle. אבל צאן אגב גיזותיה, aval tzon agav gizoteiha,
but sheep with its wool, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe you couldn't.
You know, and so this is saying the reverse. Before we said
sheep with its wool it's more of one unit. It's physically connected.
But here the גמרא Gemara says, but you could have said that
even if I had known wine with the bottle, I wouldn't have
known sheep with its wool. Cause you can't remove the bottle from
the wine, I mean without putting the wine in some other container.
Wine can't exist without a container. Sheep can exist without their shearings.
So I have both to tell me sheep and the shearings and
wine in the bottle because I couldn't have learned one from the
other. כתב רחמנא צאן, katav Rachmana tzon, it tells me sheep, דאפילו
אגב גיזותיה, d'afilu agav gizoteiha, that even with its shearings. But here's
what I don't get. בבקר למה לי? b'vakar lama li? There's no
need to tell me cattle. Because if you're telling me you can
buy the sheep with the shearings,
certainly you can buy the animal with its skin because the shearings
is less a part of the animal than the skin. I keep
on saying shearings, I mean the
wool.
וכי תימא איצטריך
משום דהוי טפי מגיזותיה,
v'ki
teima
itztarich mishum d'havei tfei migizoteiha, if you say it should be more
than the wool, אי לאו דכתב רחמנא בבקר, ei lav d'katav Rachmana
b'vakar, had the Torah not written בבקר, b'vakar, הוה אמינא hava amina
I would say צאן אגב עורה אין אגב גיזותיה לא, tzon agav
ora in agav gizoteiha lo, that sheep you can only buy if
it's already been sheared, only with its skin, but you cannot buy
with the wool attached. I might have thought that צאן tzon does
not mean with the wool. וכתב רחמנא בבקר, v'katav Rachmana b'vakar, the
Torah had to write בבקר b'vakar לאתויי עורות, l'atuyei orot, to tell
me no, no, no, I already know the idea of skin from
the idea of cattle. ואיצטריך צאן, v'itztarich tzon, and therefore why is
it saying also sheep? לאתויי גיזותיה, l'atuyei gizoteiha, to tell me even
the shearings. So no, don't tell me that. I still don't need
the word בבקר. b'vakar. אי לאו דכתב רחמנא בבקר, ei lav d'katav
Rachmana b'vakar, if it did not say בבקר, b'vakar, לא הוה אמינא
צאן אגב עורה אין אגב גיזותיה לא, lo hava amina tzon agav
ora in agav gizoteiha lo, I never would have thought that sheep
is talking about only with its skin without its wool. דאם כן,
d'im kein, if the Torah only allowed the skin of an animal
and not the wool, לכתוב רחמנא בבקר, lichtov Rachmana b'vakar, don't tell
me צאן. tzon. Give me an example of something that only has
skin, say
cattle.
דממילא ידענא צאן, d'mmeila yadana tzon, and צאן tzon would be less
aside. וכיון דכתב רחמנא צאן, v'keivan d'katav Rachmana tzon, so why if
once the Torah has chosen to write sheep, if you're going to
say sheep instead of cattle, what makes sheep distinct? That they have
wool. So צאן tzon tells me what? דאפילו אגב גיזותיה, d'afilu agav
gizoteiha, you can use your מעשר ma'aser money for it even with
its wool, even though some of the money is going towards the
wool. So once we see that you can use your מעשר ma'aser
money for the sheep with the wool, we're back to our question
בבקר למה לי? b'vakar lama li? Okay, so that was a very
long discussion why you needed all the words, but the basic point
here is
is that the idea is
השתא
צאן אגב גיזותיה משתבן,
hashta tzon
agav gizoteiha mishteban, if you can buy the sheep with its wool,
בבקר אגב עורה מיבעי? b'vakar agav ora miba'ei? Is there any question
you could buy the cattle with its skin? והיינו דקאמר רבי יוחנן,
v'hainu d'ka'amar Rabbi Yochanan, and that's what Rabbi Yochanan said, מאן דמתרגם
לי בבקר אליבא דבן בג בג, man d'mtargem lei b'vakar aliba d'Ben
Bag Bag, if somebody can tell me why בבקר b'vakar Ben Bag
Bag needs the word בבקר, b'vakar, מובלינא מאני אבתריה לבי מסותי, movlina
manei avatrei l'bei masusei, I'll carry his clothes after him to the
bathhouse. Okay, so that was a very long explanation, but ultimately the
point here is is that the idea is הבלעה, havla'ah, yes you
really cannot use מעשר ma'aser money on salt water, you can only
use it on oil, but the חידוש chiddush is when you make
a mix that contains everything, some of the money could be going
to the salt water since there is the element of the oil
in there that the מעשר ma'aser is going, that is the principle
of הבלעה havla'ah and the same way you can buy a whole
sheep, a whole cow, the wine with the bottle and the מעשר
ma'aser money could go to all of it because it's בהבלעה. b'havla'ah.
It's sort of swallowed up, it's all part of the same unit.
Now, I should say תוספות Tosafot makes the point, so if we're
talking only with the oil, presumably when we said you could use
it for עירוב, eruv, we were also talking about only with the
oil. Okay? Right? Only with oil mixed in, if presumably we're talking
about the same thing. So he says what's the חידוש chiddush then?
We know you can make an עירוב eruv with oil. So again
he says the same point, the חידוש chiddush is the amount for
שתי סעודות shtei seudos doesn't have to be just from the oil,
it could be from the combination of the oil with the salt
water, but again you need that fundamental oil there to count. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara is going to turn to this question about
what can you use מעשר ma'aser money for and I've already raised
the issue about גידולי קרקע. gidulei karka. So let's take a look.
You know, about the Gros' point about the about the mushrooms and
other fungi. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, במאי קמיפלגי רבי
יהודה בן גדיש ורבי אליעזר והני תנאי דלקמן? B'mai kamiflagi Rabbi Yehuda
ben Gadish v'Rabbi Eliezer v'hani tannai d'lekaman? So we quoted רבי יהודה
בן גדיש Rabbi Yehuda ben Gadish and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that
said fish that were debating fish brine, but they both agree that
fish is a legitimate use. So on the one hand they say
fish is good, but we'll see other תנאים tannaim saying that fish
is not good. So what is that
debate? So the
גמרא Gemara says רבי יהודה בן גדיש ורבי אליעזר דרשי. Rabbi Yehuda
ben Gadish v'Rabbi Eliezer darshi. רבי יהודה בן גדיש Rabbi Yehuda ben
Gadish רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer דרשי ריבויי ומיעוטי. darshi ribbuy u'mi'utei. Here's
finally the פסוק pasuk of מעשר Maaser money and what it might
be limited to. ונתת הכסף בכל אשר תאוה נפשך, V'nasatah hakesef bechol
asher te'aveh nafshecha, you should spend the money with all that your
heart desires. ריבה, riba, that's a general inclusive verse. בבקר ובצאן וביין
ובשכר, babakar uvatzon uvayayin uvashechar,
cattle and sheep and wine and mead. מיעט, mi'et, those are limiting
words. ובכל אשר תשאלך נפשך, uvechol asher tishalcha nafshecha, anything your heart
desires. חזר וריבה, chazar v'riba, it's again an inclusive word. ריבוי ומיעוט
וריבוי, ribbuy u'mi'ut u'ribbuy, inclusive and limiting and inclusive. ריבה הכל, riba
hakol, so it includes everything. ריבי כל מילי, ribboy kol mili, it
sounds very repetitive, what does it include? ריבי כל מילי, ribboy kol
mili, absolutely everything. ומאי מיעט? u'mai mi'et? What's the one thing it
excludes? רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer מיעט ציר, mi'et tzir, for רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer it excludes fish brine. ורבי יהודה בן גדיש v'Rabbi Yehuda
ben Gadish מיעט מים ומלח, mi'et mayim u'melach, and according to רבי
יהודה בן גדיש Rabbi Yehuda ben Gadish it excludes just salt plain
salt water. But fish certainly would be okay. The basic point is
like this. There are two ways, two hermeneutics to interpret פסוקים, psukim,
one from the school of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and the other
from the school of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. One is the one
we're familiar with which is כלל ופרט וכלל, Klal Prat u'Klal, which
we're about to get to. כלל ופרט וכלל Klal Prat u'Klal basically
says like this. When you have a כלל, klal, it's everything. כלל
ופרט, klal u'prat, you assume it's limited to the specifics of the
פרט. prat. When you have כלל ופרט וכלל klal prat u'klal then
you say everything similar to the פרט. prat. That's what we're familiar
with. ריבה ומיעט ribba u'mi'et does the same thing, but it basically
says you start one step ahead. When you have a ריבה ומיעט,
ribba u'mi'et, it's the same as the כלל ופרט klal u'prat but
it uses different terms to describe it. Already at that stage we
said if all we wanted to do was limit it to the
specifics, why did you have the broader word in the beginning? So
but it says already by stage two you're at the other guy's
stage three. By ריבוי ומיעוט ribbuy u'mi'ut you're already saying everything similar
to the list. So then if you have ריבוי מיעוט וריבוי, ribbuy
mi'et v'ribbuy, you have another broadening verse, so then it's really everything
is included. That's what it means ריבי כל מילי, ribboy kol mili,
and all you do is you exclude the thing that is most
dissimilar. So what's most dissimilar from this? Salt water, maybe brine, things
that are total really like mineral outside of the animal and vegetable
category. That's what we're
excluding. And therefore they would all agree that fish are included. Let's
just see what the other approach is. והני תנאי דרשי כלל ופרט.
v'hani tannai darshi klal u'prat. The other approach does a כלל, klal,
uses the כלל ופרט klal prat methodology, which is a more limited
one. It gets to a more limited list. דתניא, detanya, ונתת הכסף
בכל אשר תאוה נפשך, v'nasatah hakesef bechol asher te'aveh nafshecha, כלל. klal.
בבקר ובצאן וביין ובשכר, babakar uvatzon uvayayin uvashechar, פרט. prat. ובכל אשר
תשאלך נפשך, uvechol asher tishalcha nafshecha, חזר וכלל. chazar v'klal. Exact same
thing, except uses the phrase כלל ופרט. klal u'prat. כלל ופרט וכלל,
klal u'prat u'klal, general limiting and general. אי אתה דן אלא כעין
הפרט. ee ata dan ela k'ein haprat. So with all three of
them together, you can only and it's still has to be the
conclusion is it has to be similar to the specific list. So
whereas the other approach would say as long as it's not completely
dissimilar, this says כלל ופרט וכלל klal prat u'klal it has to
be similar to the specific list. So what does that mean? מה
הפרט מפורש, mah haprat meforash, the same way by this list we
have פרי מפרי, p'ri mi'p'ri, it's a product that comes from a
product, you know it's something that is a fruit in the abstract
sense. We'll see what that
excludes. But וגידולי קרקע, v'gidulei karka, and it grows from the
ground. אף כל פרי מפרי וגידולי קרקע. af kol p'ri mi'p'ri v'gidulei
karka. So it has to be things that are a fruit from
a fruit, meaning not something like water or salt or whatever, something
that is produced from something else that was produced, and it has
to grow from the ground and therefore we would exclude what? We
would exclude fish. Fish don't grow from the ground. So we will
pick up with this tomorrow to see this debate. One approach says
everything is included except basically salt water, things that are not part
of the animal vegetable category. And the other approach says it has
to be similar to the list and has very specific criteria, גידולי
קרקע, gidulei karka, פרי מפרי p'ri mi'p'ri and so on and gets
into the issue of the הגר"א ha'Gra's point about mushrooms being the
way the הגר"א ha'Gra understood being excluded because it's not גידולי קרקע.
gidulei karka. So we will see more of this
tomorrow.